And this...Emm...is going to use
这次我们要用到...
some of the techniques we learned last time
一些上一节课所学到的技术
with respect to amortized analysis.
也就是平摊分析课上内容
And, what's neat about what we're going to talk about today
今天要讲的内容非常酷炫
is it's a way of comparing algorithms
是一种比较不同算法的方法
that are so-called online algorithms.
用来比较所谓的在线算法
And we're going to introduce this notion with
在讲这个算法之前
a problem which is called self organizing lists.
我们先用一个自组织表的问题来引入
OK, and so the set up for this problem is that
好的 先说说已知条件
we have a list, L, of n elements.
我们有一个表L 里面有n个元素
And, we have an operation.
我们定义了一个操作
Woops, I've got to spell things right,
咕  差点写错字了
access of x, which accesses item x in the list.
访问x操作 也就是访问表里的元素x
It could be by searching,
它可能是搜索
or it could be however you want to do it.
也可能是其他的操作
But basically, it goes and touches that element.
总之 它需要进入表里 接触到这个元素
And we were to say the cost of that operation is
而这个操作的代价就等于
whatever the rank of x is in the list,
x在表里的排位
which is just the distance of x from the head of the list.
换句话说 就是从表头到x的距离
And the other thing that we can do
而我们想要做的其他操作
is that the algorithm can do,
也同样是这个算法需要做的操作
so this is what the user would do.
这个是用户会用到的操作
He just simply runs a whole bunch of accesses on the list,
用户对表进行一系列的访问
OK, accessing one element after another
把元素一个一个访问个遍
in any order that he or she cares to.
按照他或她想要的顺序
And then, L can be reordered, however,
然后 L的顺序还可以重新调整
by transposing adjacent elements.
只要置换相邻元素就可以了
And the cost for that is one.
而置换操作的代价只要1
So, for example,
那么 举个栗子
suppose the list is the following.
假设我们的表是这样的
OK, I missed something here.
喔呜 我是不是侧漏了些东西？
It doesn't matter.
算了 稍微漏点霸气而已
Well, I'll just make it be what I have
我还是把它改成跟我小抄一样吧
so that it matches the online video.
这样就能和视频吻合了
OK, so here we have a list.
好的 我们这有一个表
And so, if I do something like access element 14 here,
例如我要访问元素14
the element of key 14,
键值为14的元素
OK, that this costs me one, two, three, four.
好的 这步操作的代价是1 2 3 4
So here the cost is four to access.
那么 这次访问的代价是4
And so, we're going to have some sequence of accesses
接下来 我们要做一系列的访问操作
that the user is going to do.
用户要做这一系列操作
And obviously, if something is accessed more frequently,
显然 某些元素会访问得更加频繁
we'd like to move it up to the front of the list
我们想要把它放到表的前排
so that you don't have to search as far.
这样你搜索时 就不用走得太远
OK, and to do that, if I want to transpose something,
好的 这样的话 如果我们要置换元素
so, for example, if I transpose three and 50,
比如说 如果我要置换3和50
that just costs me one.
这步花费只需要1
OK, so then I would make this be 50,
好的 我把这个换成50
and make this be three.
把这个换成3
OK, sorry, normally you just do it by swapping pointers.
抱歉 一般来说 你们只需要交换指针就好了
OK, so those are the two operations.
好的 这是我们定义的两个操作
And, we are going to do this in what's called an online fashion.
接下来 我们要用“在线”的形式来完成它
So, let's just define online.
那么 我们先给“在线”下定义
So, a sequence, S, of operations
一个操作序列S
is provided one at a time for each operation.
每次只发送一步的操作请求
An online algorithm must execute the operation immediately
而在线算法则必须马上完成这步操作
without getting a chance to look at
而不管接下来
what else is coming in the sequence.
会出现什么操作
So, when you make your decision for the first element,
那么 当你考虑序列中的第一项操作时
you don't get to see ahead
你是不考虑后面的操作的
as to what the second, or third, or whatever is.
无论是第二个 第三个 哪个都一样
And the second one you get,
轮到第二项操作时
and you have to make your decision as to what to do
你就只能执行这一项操作
and so forth.
以此类推
So, that's an online algorithm.
这就是在线算法
Similarly, an off-line algorithm,
反过来 离线算法
OK, may see all of S in advance.
它可以预先看过所有的操作
OK, so you can see
好的 也就是说
an off-line algorithm gets to see the whole sequence,
离线的算法需要预读整个序列
and then decide what it wants to do about
然后再决定要怎么处理...
element one, element two, or whatever.
操作1 操作2 等等
So an off-line algorithm can look at the whole sequence and say,
所以 离线算法可以预读整个序列
OK, I can see that item number 17 is being accessed a lot,
它可以提前知道17会被多次访问
or early on move him up closer to the front of the list,
然后把它放到更靠近表头的地方
and then the accesses cost less for the off-line algorithm.
这样离线算法的访问花费就会更少
The online algorithm doesn't get to see any of that.
但在线算法却不能预知未来
OK, so this is sort of like,
所以 这就有点像
if you're familiar with the game Tetris.
如果你熟悉俄罗斯方块的话
OK, and Tetris,
对 俄罗斯方块
you get one shape after another that starts coming down,
那些方块是一个接一个的往下掉的
and you have to twiddle it,
你要旋转它
and move it to the side, and drop it into place.
然后左右移动它 把它放到合适的地方
And there, sometimes you get a one step look-ahead
而在游戏中 你只能往前看一步
on some of them so you can see what the next shape is,
你只能看到下一个要出现的方块是什么
but often it's purely online.
但通常下一个方块是在线计算的
You don't get to see that next shape or whatever,
你没法看到再下一个方块什么的
and you have to make a decision for each one.
你必须一步作一个决定
And you make a decision,
当你作出了一个决定
and you realize that the next shape,
再看到下一个方块 又突然发现
ah, if you had made a different decision
啊 如果刚才作另一种决定的话
it would have been better.
结果要更好一点
OK, so that's the kind of problem.
好吧 就是这一类问题
Off-line Tetris would be,
离线俄罗斯方块什么样子的呢
I get to see the whole sequence of shapes.
我能看到往后的整串方块
And now let me decide what I'm going to do with this one.
然后 我再来决定这个方块放哪好
OK, and so, in this, the goal is for any of the algorithms,
好的 这其中 我们的目标是
either online or off-line is to minimize the total cost,
不管是在线离线 都是把代价最小化
which we'll denote by,
我们把它记为
☆★☆★☆, I forgot to name this.
我的母星啊 我忘了给个名字
This is algorithm A here.
这个是A算法
The total cost, C_A of S,
总代价 C_A(S)
OK, so the cost of algorithm A on the sequence, S.
好的 这是用A算法计算序列S的代价
That's just the notation we'll use for what the total cost is.
我们用这个记号来表示总代价
So, any questions about the setup to this problem?
那么 对这个问题的定义有没有问题？
So, we have an online problem.
那么 我们遇到了在线计算的问题
We're going to get these things one at a time,
我们一次只能做一步计算
OK, and we have to decide what to do.
好的 看看我们要做的是什么
So, let's do a worst-case analysis for this.
呃 我们分析它的最坏情况
OK, so if we're doing a worst-case analysis,
如果我们要分析它的最坏情况
we can view that we have an adversary that
我们假想我们有个宿敌
we are playing against who's going to provide the sequence.
他会给我们安排整个俄罗斯方块的顺序
The user is going to be able to see what we do.
对手还能看到我们所做的决定
And so, what's the adversary strategy?
这样的话 宿敌会用什么对策？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Thwart our plots, yes, that's his idea.
[教授]:破坏我们的计划 对 这是对手的想法
And how is he going to thwart them, or she?
那他或她准备怎么破？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Which is what for this problem?
[教授]:这个问题怎么搞？
What's he going to do?
他会怎么做？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Yeah. No matter how we reorder elements using the transposes,
[教授]:对 无论我们怎么重排列表中的元素
he's going to look at every step and say,
他都一步步看着 然后说
what's the last element?
最后是哪个元素？
That's the one I'm going to access, right?
那才是他要我们访问的元素 是吧？
So, the adversary always,
那么 对手总是
always accesses the tail element of L.
总是(要我们)访问序列L的末尾的元素
No matter what it is, no matter how we reorder things,
不管它是啥 不管我们怎么重排列表
OK, for each one, adversary just accesses the tail.
好的 对于每一次 对手只(要我们)访问末尾
So the cost of this, of any algorithm, then,
那么总的代价 对于任意一种算法 都会有
is going to be omega size of S times n,
序列S的大小乘以n
OK, because you're always going to pay for every sequence.
好的 因为 对于每个操作序列来说
You're going to have to go in to pay a cost of n,
你都要走到底 所以代价是n
OK, for every element in the sequence.
对于序列中的每一步访问皆然
OK, so not terribly in the worst-case.
好的 所以最坏情况不会很差
Not terribly good.
还好吧
So, people in studying this problem: question?
研究这个问题的人...什么事？
[Student]: Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:That analysis is for the online algorithm, right.
[教授]:这是在线算法的复杂度分析 是的
The off-line algorithm, right,
离线算法 是的
if you named those things, that's right.
你可以这么叫它们 没问题
OK, so we're looking at trying to solve this in an off-line sense,
我们尝试在离线的情况下去解决这个问题
sorry, in an online sense.
不好意思 是在线
OK, and so the point is that for the online algorithm,
好的 就是说在线算法
the adversary can be incredibly mean,
对手可能是令人发狂的难度
OK, and just always access the thing at the end, OK?
总是要我们访问末尾元素 好吧？
So, what sort of the history of this problem is,
这个问题的由来是
that people said, well,
人们想 额
if I can't do well in the worst-case,
如果最坏情况已经无法挽回了
maybe I should be looking at average case,
可能我得看看平均情况会如何
OK, and look at, say,
那我们就来看看
the different elements having some probability distribution.
不同元素有不同概率分布的情况
OK, so the average case analysis,
好的 分析平均情况
OK, let's suppose that element x is accessed,
假如说 元素x被访问到
with probability P of x.
它的概率是P(x)
OK, so suppose that
好的 我们假设
we have some a priori distribution on the elements.
元素被访问的事件有一个先验分布
Then the expected cost of the algorithm on a sequence,
对于一个访问序列 某种算法的期望代价
OK, so if I put all the elements into some order,
如果说 我先设置一种元素的顺序
OK, and don't try to reorder,
之后就不再改变它
but just simply look at, is there a static ordering
然后看一下 会不会有某种固定的顺序
that would work well for a distribution?
特别适合某种分布？
It's just going to be, by definition of expectation,
按照期望的定义
the probability of x times, in this case, the cost,
就是访问x的概率乘上 在这里是代价
which is the rank of x in whatever that ordering is
也就是x的排位 排位与顺序相关
that I decide I'm going to use.
顺序是我们设置的
OK, and this is minimized when?
什么时候期望最小？
So, this is just the definition of expectations:
所以这个就是期望的定义
the probability that I access x times the cost
访问x的概率乘以代价
summed over all the elements.
然后对所有元素求总和
And the cost is just going to be its position in the list.
这个代价就是元素在表里的位置
So, when is this value,
所以 这个值
this summation, going to be minimized?
这个总和 什么时候最小?
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:When the element is most likely as the lowest rank,
[教授]:当最有可能用到的元素 有最低的排位时
and then what, what about the other element?
然后呢 其它的元素呢
OK, so what does that mean?
好的 那是什么意思？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Yeah, sort them, yeah,
[教授]:嗯 把他们排好序 嗯
sort them on the basis of decreasing probability, OK?
按访问概率排成降序 对吧？
So, it's minimized when L is sorted,
所以 L这样排序的时候期望最小
OK, in decreasing order with respect to P.
按访问概率P递减的顺序
OK, so just sort them with the most likely one at the front,
好吧 把最大概率的排在最前
and then just decreasing probability.
然后按概率递减
That way, whenever I access something with some probability,
因为 当我有概率地访问元素时
OK, I'm going to access,
我将会访问那些
it's more likely that I'm going to access.
更可能访问到的元素
And that's not too difficult to actually prove.
其实这点也不难证明
You just look at, suppose there were two that were out of order,
你只需想想 假设两个元素顺序反了
and show that if you swap them,
你只要证明 通过交换
you would improve this optimization function.
你就能优化这个函数的性能
OK, so if you didn't know it,
好的 如果你并不知道（访问概率）
this suggests the following heuristic,
那么我们也能得到如下的启发
OK, which is simply keep account of the number of times
它只是记录每个元素...
each element is accessed,
被访问的次数
and maintain the list in order of decreasing count.
并按访问次数递减的顺序 维护这个表
OK, so whenever something is accessed,
好的 当一个元素被访问到
increment its count,
它的计数加一
OK, and that will move it,
这样 他就会移动
at most, one position,
最多一个位置
which only costs me one transposed to move it,
置换一次代价只是1
perhaps, forward.
它可能向前
OK, actually, I guess it could be more
实际上 我觉得它可能移得更前
if you have a whole bunch of ties, right?
当元素并列在一起的时候 对吧？
Yeah. So, it could cost more.
是的 它可能花更多代价
But the idea is, over time,
但思路就是 随着时间推移
the law of large numbers says that
依照大数定理
this is going to approach the probability distribution.
它将会和概率分布一致的
The frequency with which you access this,
你访问这一个的频数
divided by the total number of accesses,
除以访问总数
will be the probability.
就得到了概率
And so, therefore you will get things in decreasing probability,
所以 你的表就会是按出现概率递减排列的
OK, assuming that there is some distribution that
好吧 假设这里有一种分布
all of these elements are chosen according to,
所有元素是按照分布来被选择
or accessed according to.
或者被访问到
So, it doesn't seem like there's that much more
这听起来并不像是
you could really do here.
你可以做得到的事
And that's why I think
这就是为什么我认为
this notion of competitive analysis is so persuasive,
竞争分析这个概念有说服力
because it's really amazingly strong, OK?
就是因为它真的很强大 对吧？
And it came about because of what people were doing in practice.
它是从人们的实践中获得的
So practice, what people implement it
实际应用中 人们是在
was a so-called move to front heuristic.
所谓的移前启发式中实现它的
OK, and the basic idea was,
它基本思想是
after you access an element,
当你访问了一个元素后
just move it up to the front.
就把它移动到前面
OK, that only doubles the cost of accessing the element
这仅仅是将访问该元素的代价加倍了
because I go and I access it,
因为我访问它时
chasing it down paying the rank,
先要花它排位的代价找到它
and then I have to do rank number of transposes
然后又要花它排位的代价来置换它
to bring it back to the front.
把它置换到前面去
So, it only cost me a factor of two, and now,
但这也只是多花了一倍的代价 而现在
if it happens to be a frequently accessed elements,
如果访问到的是高频元素
over time you would hope that
渐渐地你发现
the most likely elements were near the front of that list.
最可能被访问到的元素就都在表头
So, after accessing x,
所以 访问了x后
move x to the head of the list using transposes,
把x置换到表头去
and the cost is just equal to twice the rank in L of x,
这个代价刚好等于x的排名乘以2
OK, where the two here has two parts.
这个“2”要一分为二
One is the access,
第一部分是访问
and the other is the transposes.
第二部分是置换
OK, so that's sort of what they did.
好的 这就是它们做的
And one of the nice properties of this is that
还有个好处就是
if it turns out that there is locality in the access pattern,
假如发现它的访问模式是局部性的
if it's not just a static distribution,
不是一个静态分布
but rather once I've accessed something,
而是一旦我访问了某个数
if it's more likely I'm going to access it again,
以后我就更有可能访问到它
which tends to be the case for many input types of patterns,
许多输入的模式都有这种情况
this responds well to locality
这种机制则很适合处理局部性
because it's going to be up near the front
因为这样 元素就总会在表头附近
if I access it very soon after I've accessed.
当我访问过它一次 下次很快就找到了
So, there is what's called temporal locality,
这叫做暂时局部性
meaning that in time, I tend to access,
也就是在某段时间内的访问趋势
so it may be that I access some thing's very hot for awhile;
在某段时间内 一些元素可能非常热门
then it gets very cold.
慢慢地 它又变冷门了
This type of algorithm responds very well
这种算法对于元素的热门度
to the hotness of the accessing.
有非常好的反应
OK, so it responds well to locality in S.
好的 对于S的局部性的反应相当好
So, this is sort of what was known
下面要介绍一个著名的分析技术
up to the point that a very famous paper was written
它出自一篇非常著名的论文
by Danny Sleator and Bob Tarjan,
作者的名字就是B.T.大.神.
where they took a totally different approach
他们采用了一种革新的方法
to looking at this kind of problem.
来研究这种问题
OK, and it's an approach that matter you see everywhere
这种方法的影响到处可见
from analysis of caching and high-performance processors
从高速缓存分析 到高性能处理器分析
to analyses of disk paging
再到硬盘分页管理分析
to just a huge number of applications of this basic technique.
还有一大批应用 都用到了这种基本技术
And, that's the technique of competitive analysis.
这种技术就是竞争分析
OK, so here's the definition.
下面是定义
So, online algorithm A is alpha competitive.
我们称 在线算法A是α竞争的
If there exists a constant, k,
如果存在一个常数k
such that for any sequence, S, of operations,
满足对于任意操作序列S
the cost of S using algorithm A
运用算法A的代价
is bounded by alpha times the cost of opt,
不超过α乘以opt的代价
where opt is the optimal offline algorithm.
opt指的是最优的离线算法
OK, so the optimal off-line,
好的 最优的离线算法
the one that knows the whole sequence
它一开始就预读了整个序列
and does the absolute best it could do on that sequence,
那么 它当然能对这个数列做最好的处理
OK, that's this cost here.
这就是它的代价
This is sometimes called God's algorithm,
有时候 它被称为上帝算法
OK, not to bring religion into the classroom,
我们不是在课堂上讲耶稣
or to offend anybody,
也不是要冒犯在座的无神论者
but that is what people sometimes call it.
但人们有时就这样叫它
OK, so the fully omniscient knows
上帝是无所不知的
absolutely the best thing that could be done,
它绝对知道最优的策略
sees into the future, the whole works, OK?
能预知未来 了解一切运作 好吧？
It gets to apply that.
它能做到那样
That's what opts algorithm is.
这就是最优算法
And, what we're saying is that
我们要说的是
the cost is basically whatever this alpha factor is.
代价是跟这个α有关
It could be a function of things,
它可能是一个函数式
or it could be a constant,
又可能是个常数
OK, times whatever the best algorithm is.
然后 乘以最优算法
Plus, there's a potential for a constant out here.
再加上一个可能出现的常数
OK, so for example, if alpha is two,
举个例子 如果α等于2
and we say it's two competitive,
我们说这个是双竞争的
that means you're going to do, at worst,
意思是 你在最差情况下
twice the algorithm that has all the information.
代价是最优算法的两倍
But you're doing it online, for example.
但你的算法是在线的 比方说
OK, it's a really pretty powerful notion.
它真的是个非常强大的概念
And what's interesting about this,
而且有趣的是
it's not even clear these things should exist to my mind.
我甚至还不知道这些是什么
OK, what's pretty remarkable about this,
好吧 我觉得它最出色的一点
I think, is that there is no assumption of distribution,
就是不用对元素分布作出假设
of probability distribution or anything.
不对概率分布作出假设
It's whatever the sequence is that you give it.
无论你给的是什么序列
You are within a factor of alpha, essentially,
原则上 代价上限都受α因子控制着
of the best algorithm, OK,
最优算法的α倍
which is pretty remarkable.
这点真的很出色
OK, and so, we're going to prove the following theorem,
接下来 我们要证明一个定理
which is the one that Sleator and Tarjan proved.
它已经被B.T.大.神.证明过了
And that is that MTF is four competitive
这个定理是 自组织表中的MTF算法
for self organizing lists.
是四竞争的
OK, so the idea here is that suppose the adversary says,
好的 假设我们的宿敌说
oh, I'm always going to access the thing at the end of the list
哼 人家就是要访问列表的最后一个元素
like we said in the beginning.
就像一开始说的那样
So, the adversary says,
宿敌很傲娇
I'm always going to access the thing there.
我就是要访问那个元素
I'm going to make MTF work really bad,
我要使得MTF效果非常差
because you're going to go and move that thing
因为你想把那个元素
all the way up to the front.
一直移到最前面
And I'm just going to access the thing way at the end again.
那人家就再访问列表最后的那个元素
OK, well it turns out,
这样一来
yeah, that's a bad sequence for move to front,
这种访问的顺序对MTF来说非常糟糕
OK, and it will take a long time.
它要花费大量的时间
But it turns out God couldn't have done better,
但上帝依然表示毫无压力
OK, by more than a factor of four
而且α因子还不会大于4
no matter how long the list is.
无论列表有多长
OK, that's pretty amazing.
真的很神啊
So yeah that's a bad sequence.
虽然访问序列真的很恶劣
But, if there's a way that
但是 如果有方法
the sequence exhibits any kind of locality
能使这个序列表现出局部性
or anything that can be taken advantage of,
或者任何能被加以利用的性质
if you could see the whole thing,
如果你预知整个序列
MTF takes advantage of it too,
MTF也可以受益
OK, within a factor of four.
总之它的代价总在4倍之内
OK, it's a pretty remarkable theorem,
它真的是个很出色的定理
and it's the basis of many types of analysis of online algorithms.
它还是许多在线算法的分析的基础
Almost all online algorithms today are analyzed
而现在 几乎所有的在线算法分析
using some kind of competitive analysis.
都用到竞争分析
OK, not always.
好吧 不是所有
Sometimes you do probabilistic analysis, or whatever,
有时候你做的是概率分析 或者别的
but the dominant thing is to competitive analysis
但最主流的还是竞争分析
because then you don't have to make any statistical assumptions.
因为你用不着去做统计学上的假设
OK, just prove that it works well no matter how.
你只需要证明无论如何 算法的效果都很好
This is remarkable, I think.
这简直让人热血沸腾 有木有？
Isn't it remarkable?
我整个人都斯巴达了！
So, let's prove this theorem,
那我们来证明这个定理
we're just going to spend the rest of the lecture on this proof.
这堂课剩下的时间都用来证明这个
OK, and the proof in some ways is not hard,
从某些角度看 证明这个不难
but it's also not necessarily completely intuitive.
但它又不是那么的直观
So, you will have to pay attention.
所以 你们要打醒十二分精神
OK, so let's get some notation down.
我们先记下一些符号
Let's let L_i be MTF's list after the i'th access.
设L_i为第i次访问后的MTF表
And, let's let L be opt's list after the i'th access.
然后设L_i*为第i次后的最优表
OK, so generally what I'll do is
所以 我一般会...
I'll put a star if we are talking about opt,
加一个*号来表示最优表
and have nothing if we're talking about MTF.
在讨论MTF时什么也不加
OK, so that's going to be the list.
这就是我们的表
So, we can say, what's the list?
我们说 这个表是什么？
So, we're going to set it up where we have one in operation
我们构建表的过程 有一步操作
that transforms list i minus one into list i.
它能把L_(i-1)转变为L_i
OK, that's what the i'th operation does.
这就是第i个操作做的事情
OK, and move to front does it by moving
把元素移到最前
whatever the thing that was accessed to the front.
只要被访问到 就移到最前面去
And opt does whatever opt thinks is the best thing to do.
而最优算法只会做它认为最适合的操作
We don't know.
内容我们不清楚
So, we're going to let c_i be MTF's cost for the I'th operation.
那么我们设c_i为MTF表的第i个操作的代价
And that's just twice the rank in L_i minus one of x
代价等于x在L_(i-1)中的排位的两倍
if the operation accesses x, OK,
如果x被访问到 好的
two times the rank in L_i minus one
2乘以在L_(i-1)里的排位
because we're going to be accessing it in L_i minus one
因为我们是在L_(i-1)表里访问它的
and transforming it into L_i.
然后把表转变为L_i
And similarly, we'll let c_i star
同样地 我们令c_i
be opt's cost for the i'th operation.
为最优表的第i个操作的代价
And that's just equal to, well,
而这个就等于
to access it, it's going to be the rank in L_i minus one star,
在表L_(i-1)*里访问x的代价
whatever its list is of x at that step,
也就是x在那一步的排位
because it's got to access it.
因为我们要访问它
And then, some number of transposes,
然后 若干次置换操作
t_i if opt forms t_i transposes.
t_i是指 最优表做了t_i次置换
OK, so we have the setup where we have
好的 我们构建了一个模型
two different lists that are being managed,
我们有两种不同的列表
and we have different costs in the list.
两种表的代价也不同
And, we're interested in is comparing in some way
我们希望给它们做个比较
MTF's list with opt's list at any point in time.
MTF表与最优表 在任意一个时间点上作比较
And, how do you think we're going to do that?
然后 你们认为要怎么做？
What technique do you think we should use
我们该用什么方法
to compare these two lists,
来比较这两个表
general technique from last lecture?
上节课说的一般方法？
Well, it is going to be amortized, but what?
平摊分析 但怎么用？
How are we going to compare them?
我们怎么样比较？
What technique did we learn last time?
我们上节课学了什么方法？
Potential function, good.
势能函数 没错
OK, we're going to define a potential function,
我们先去定义一个势能函数
OK, that measures how far apart these two lists are.
用来计算这两个表的距离
OK, and the idea is, if,
好的 做法是
let's define that and then we'll take a look at it.
我们先定义 然后再观察它
So, we're going to define the potential function phi
我们定义一个势能函数Φ
mapping the set of MTF's lists into the real numbers
把MTF的表映射为实数
by the following.
定义如下
phi of L_i is going to be twice the cardinality of this set.
Φ（L_i)等于2乘以集合的势
OK, so this is the precedes-operation and list, i.
好的 这是列表i里的优先操作
So, we can define a relationship between any two elements
我们可以定义两个元素间的关系
that says that x precedes y in L_i if,
如果在L_i中 x优先于y的话
as I'm accessing it from the head, I hit x first.
那从表头向下走 我会先遇到x
OK, so what I'm interested in, here, are
这里我关心的是
in some sense the disagreements between the two lists.
这两个表之间的不同点
This is where x precedes y in MTF's list,
在MTF表里x优先于y
but y precedes x in opt's list.
在最优表里y优先于x
They disagree, OK?
它们有分歧 对吧
And, what we're interested in is the cardinality of the set.
我们也关心集合的势
And we're going to multiply it by two.
我们准备把它乘以二
OK, so that's equal to two times;
这个就等于两倍
so there is a name for this type of thing.
这个东西有个名字的
We saw that when we were doing sorting.
我们在学排序的时候讲过了
Anybody remember the name?
有人知道它的名字吗？
Briefly, it was very briefly.
很短的名字 非常短
I don't expect anybody to remember, but somebody might.
你们不一定都记得 但会有人记得的吧
Inversions: good, OK,
逆序对 很好
twice the number of inversions.
逆序对的数目乘以二
So, let's just do an example.
我们来举个荔枝
So, let's say L_i is the list with five elements.
我们假设L_i有5个元素
OK, I'll use characters for the order
我们用符号表示顺序
just to keep things simple.
让事情变得简单
So, in this case phi of L_i is going to be
这种情况下 Φ(L_i)等于
twice the cardinality of the set.
集合的势的两倍
So what we want to do is see which things are out of order.
我们希望找出顺序不一致的地方
So here, I look at E and C are in this order,
所以这里 我有e和c在这里
but C and E in that order.
但是在那个序列是c和e
So, those are out of order.
所以这些是逆序的
So, that counts as one of my elements, EC,
那我们数到第一个元素（e,c）
and then, E and A, A and E.
然后是e和a  a和e
OK, so those are out of order,
这俩也是逆序的
and then ED, DE, out of order,
然后有ed de
and then EB, BE, those are out of order.
还有eb be 都是逆序
And now, I go C, A, C, A.
现在我看到c a c a
Those are in order, so it doesn't count.
它们是顺序的
CD, CD, CB, CB, so, nothing with C.
cd cd cb cb 所以c没有逆序
Then, A, D, A, D, those are in order,
然后 ad ad 这些是顺序的
A, B, A, B, those are in order.
a b a b 顺序的
So then, DB, BD, so BD.
然后 db bd 所以有bd
And that's the last one.
这是最后一个了
So, that's my potential function,
这就是我的势函数
which is equal to, therefore, ten,
所以就等于 10
because the cardinality of the set is five.
因为这个集合的势等于5
I have five inversions,
我有五个逆序对
OK, between the two lists.
好的 两个列表中
so let's just check some properties of this potential function.
那么我们看看这个势函数的一些特性
The first one is notice that phi of L_i
第一个我们注意到Φ(L_i)
is greater than or equal to zero for all i.
对于任意i都大于等于0
The number of inversions might be zero,
逆序数可能等于0
but is never less than zero.
但不可能小于0
OK, it's always at least zero.
所以最小总是为0
So, that's one of the properties that we normally have
它的这一个特性
when we are dealing with potential functions.
会在势能函数中用到
And, the other thing is, well, what about phi of L_0?
然后 另外的是 Φ(L_0)等于多少？
Is that equal to zero?
等于0吗？
Well, it depends upon what list they start with.
这取决于表的初始状态
OK, so what's the initial ordering?
好的 初始排列是什么？
So, it's zero if they start with the same list.
如果两个表初始排列相同的就为0
Then there are no inversions.
它们没有逆序对
But, they might start with different lists.
但是 他们也可能从一开始就是不同的
We'll talk about different lists later on,
我们稍后会讨论一开始就不同的情况
but let's say for now that it's zero because
但是现在我们说Φ(L_0)等于0
they start with the same list.
因为一开始的序列是相同的
That seems like a fair comparison.
这样看起来才是公平的比较
OK, so we have this potential function now
好的 现在我们有了这个势函数
that's counting up, how different are these two lists.
它计算的是 这两个表有多不同
Intuitively, we're going to do is
直观来看 我们的情况是
the more differences there are in the list,
两个表之间的不同点越多
the more we are going to be able to have
我们就越是能够
more stored up work than we can pay for it.
储存更多的功 来为以后做准备
That's the basic idea.
基本思路就这样
So, the more that opt changes the list,
最优算法对列表的改变越多
so it's not the same as ours,
它就跟我们越不一样了
in some sense the more we are going to be in a position as MTF
某种程度上 我们就越是能在MTF里面
to take advantage of that difference
利用列表之间的差异
in delivering up work for us to do.
产生势能来为我们服务
And we'll see how that plays out.
我们看看是怎么做到的
So, let's first also make another observation.
我们先从另一角度观察
So, how much does phi change from one transpose?
交换一次位置 Φ会改变多少？
How much does phi change from one transpose?
一次交换Φ改变多少？
So, basically that's asking,
其实就是在问
if you do a transpose,
如果做一步置换
what happens to the number of inversions?
逆序对的数目会有什么改变？
So, what happens when a transposing is done?
交换位置后会怎么样？
What's going to happen to phi?
Φ会发生什么？
What's going to happen to the number of inversions?
逆序对的数目会有什么改变？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:So, if I change, it is less than n minus one, yes,
[教授]:如果我改变了 它就小于n-1
if n is sufficiently large, yes.
当n足够大时 没错
OK, if I change, so you can think about it here.
好的 如果我改变它们 你们想下这种情况
Suppose I switch two of these elements here.
假设我交换这里的两个元素
How much are things going to change?
这样会改变多少
Yeah, it's basically one or minus one,
基本上是1或-1
OK, because a transpose creates or destroys one inversion.
交换（相邻）元素会产生或消除一个逆序对
So, if you think about it,
如果你想想
what if I change, for example, C and A,
我交换的如果是c和a
the relationship of C and A
那c和a...
to everything else in the list is going to stay the same.
跟表里其他元素的关系没有变化
The only thing, possibly, that happens is that
唯一可能发生的事情是
if they are in the same order when I transpose them,
置换前 它们的顺序相同
I've created an inversion.
置换后就变逆序了
Or, if they were in the wrong order when I transpose them,
或者 它们原本是逆序的 被我交换位置后
now they're in the right order.
成了顺序的
So therefore, the change to the potential function
因此 这个操作对于势函数的改变
is going to be plus or minus two
等于正负二
because we're counting twice the number of inversions.
因为是逆序对的数量乘以2
OK, any questions about that?
好的 有什么问题吗？
So, transposes don't change the potential very much,
所以 置换没有对势能造成多大的改变
just by one.
就只有1
It either goes up by two or down by two,
它不是加二就是减二
just by one inversion.
就一个逆序对
So now, let's take a look at how these two algorithms operate.
那现在 我们看一下这两个算法是怎么运作的
OK, so what happens when op i accesses x in the two lists?
好的 操作i访问两个列表的x会发生什么？
What's going to be going on?
会发生什么事？
To do that, let's define the following sets.
我们先要定义下面的集合
Why do I keep doing that?
为什么我总是这么做？
OK, so we're going to look at the,
好的 我们看到这里
when we access x,
当我们访问x时
we are going to look at the two lists,
我们观察这两个列表
and see what the relationship is,
然后看到它们的关系是什么
so, based on things that come before and after.
根据操作的先来后到
So, I think a picture is very helpful
我觉得有幅图片非常有用
to understand what's going on here.
可以帮助我们理解
OK, so let's let,
好的 我们设
so here's L_i minus one,
这里是L_(i-1)
and we have our list, which I'll draw like this.
我们的列表 画起来是这样的
And somewhere in there, we have x.
我们这里有个x
OK, and then we have L_i minus one star,
还有就是L_(i-1)*的
which is opt's list,
也就是最优表
OK, and he's got x somewhere else, or she.
他或她 把x放在其他位置上
OK, and so, what is this set?
好的 这个集合是什么？
This is the set of Y that come before x.
这个集合里 y在x的前面
So, that basically sets A and B.
这是集合A∪B的情况
OK, those things that come before x in both.
好的 这两个里面y都在x前面
And, some of them, the A's come before it in x,
而对于表L_(i-1)* A集合里 y在x前面
but come after it in, come before it in A,
但是... A集合里 y在x前面
but come after it in B.
B集合里 y在x的后面
OK, and similarly down here, what's this set?
下面也同样 这个集合是什么？
That's A union C, good.
A∪C 很好
And this one? Duh.
那这个呢？囧
Yeah, it better be C union D
它就是C∪D
because I've got A union B over there, and I've got x.
因为我这里有A∪B 而这里是x
So that better be everything else.
所以应该是其他的集合
OK, and here is B union D.
好的 这里是B∪D
OK, so those are the four sets that we're going to care about.
所以 这里是我们要关注的四个集合
We're actually mostly going to care about these two sets.
我们实际最关心的是这两个
OK, and we also know something about the r here.
我们这里还有个r
The position of x is going to be
记录x的位置 也就等于
the rank in L_i minus one of x.
x在L_(i-1)的排位
And here, this is r star.
然后这里 这个是r
It's just to the rank in L_i minus one star of x.
它就等于x在L_(i-1)*的排位
So, we know what these ranks are.
好 我们已经知道这些排位了
And what we're going to be interested in is,
我们要研究的是
in fact, characterizing the rank in terms of the sets.
实际上 用集合来表示这个位置
OK, so what's the position of this?
好的 那这是什么位置？
Well, the rank, we have that r is equal to the size of A.
好 排位 我们有r等于 A的大小
plus the size of B plus one.
加上B的大小再加一
OK, and r star is equal to the size of A
而r*等于A的大小
plus the size of C plus one.
加上C的大小再加上一
So, let's take a look at what happens
那么 我们看下这里发生了什么
when these two algorithms do their thing.
当这两个算法都在运作时
So, when the access to x occurs,
当它访问到x时
we move x to the front of the list.
我们把x移动到列表的开头
OK, it goes right up to the front.
好的 它跑到最前面去
So, how many inversions are created and destroyed?
那么 有多少逆序对 产生或消除了？
So, how many are created by this?
这里会产生多少？
That's probably a, how many inversions are created?
这大概有 有多少逆序对产生？
How many inversions are created?
有多少产生了？
So, we move x to the front.
所以 我们把x移到最前
So what we are concerned about is that
而我们关心的是
anything that was in one of these sets that came,
这些集合里 那些元素在变动后
where it's going to change in order versus down here.
会与下面的元素产生逆序
So, if I look in B,
如果我观察B
well, let's take a look at A.
呃 我们先看一下A
OK, so A, those are the things that are in the same order
对于A 它们都保持同样顺序的
in both.
两者之间
So, everything that's in A,
所以A集合里的所有元素
when I move x to the front,
当我把x移到最前面的时候
each thing in A is going to count for one more inversion.
每一个A的元素都产生一对逆序
Does everybody see that?
都看懂了吗？
So, I create a cardinality of A inversions.
所以 我产生的逆序对数 等于A的势
And, we are going to destroy, well,
而另一方面 我们会消除
everything in B came before x in this list,
在L_(i-1)表里 B所有元素都在x前面
and after x in this.
在L_(i-1)*里 则在后面
But after we move x,
但我移动x之后
they're in the right order.
它们的顺序则一样了
So, I'm going to destroy B inversions,
所以 我消除了B集的逆序对
cardinality of B inversions.
逆序对的个数等于B的势
So that's what happens we operate with move to front.
所以这就是我们mtf操作的结果
We destroy.
我们消除掉
We create A inversions and destroy B inversions,
我们产生A的逆序并消除B的逆序
OK, by doing this movement.
好的 通过这个移动
OK, now, let's take a look at what opt does.
好的 现在 我们看看这个最优算法做了什么
So, each transpose, we don't know what opt does.
每次置换 我们都不知道它做了什么
He might move x this way or that way. We don't know.
它可能把x移到这儿或那儿 我们不知道
But each transpose by opt,
但最优算法的每次置换
we're going to be interested in how many inversions it creates,
我们要找出它产生了多少对逆序
and we already argued that it's going to create,
我们已经讨论过
at most, one inversion per transpose.
它在一次置换中 最多产生一对逆序
So, he can't go and create more inversions, OK?
所以 他不会产生更多的逆序对 是吧？
So, let me write it over here. Thus --
那么 我把它写在这里
——the change in potential is going to be,
势能变化就是
at most, twice, A minus B plus t_i.
最大不超过两倍的A减B加上t_i
OK, so t_i, remember, was the number of transposes that
好的 t_i 记住它就是第i步的时候
opt does on the i'th step for the i'th operation.
最优表在第i次操作时 置换的次数
OK, so we're going to create the change in potential is,
好的 我们要产生的势能变化
at most, twice this function.
最大等于这条函数式的两倍
So, we are now going to look to see how we use this fact,
那么 我们看看如何运用这个事实
and these two facts, this fact and this fact, OK,
和另外两个事实 好吧
to show that opt can't be much better than MTF.
来证明最优算法也不比MTF好很多
OK, good.
好的
The way we are going to do that
我们的方法是
is look at the amortized cost of the I'th operation.
研究第i次操作的平摊代价
OK, what's MTF's amortized cost?
MTF的平摊代价是多少？
OK, and then we'll make the argument,
然后我们给出一个论断
which is the one you always make that
也就是你经常用到的
the amortized cost upper bound the true costs, OK?
平摊代价是实际代价的上限 是吧？
But the amortized cost is going to be easier to calculate.
而且平摊代价更容易计算
OK, so amortized cost is just C hat,
好的 用c^来表示均摊代价
actually, let me make sure I have lots of room here on the right,
让我看看右边够不够位置
c_i hat, which is equal to the true cost
c^i 等于实际代价
plus the change in potential.
加上势能的变化
OK, that's just the definition of amortized cost
好的 这就是平摊代价的定义
when given potential functions, OK?
其中包含了势函数 对吧？
So, what is the cost of operation i,
那么 操作i的代价是多少
OK, in this context here?
在这种情况中
OK, we accessed x there.
好的 我们访问x
What's the cost of operation i?
操作i的代价是多少？
Two times the rank of x, which is 2r.
2乘以x的排位 等于2r
OK, so 2r, that part of it.
好的2r是它的一部分
OK, plus, we have an upper bound on the change in potential.
加上 我们有个势能变化的上限
That's this.
就是这个
OK, so that's two times the cardinality of A
两倍的A的势
minus cardinality of B plus t_i.
减去B的势加上ti
OK, everybody with me?
好吧 都跟上了吗？
Yeah? OK, I see lots of nods. That's good.
嗯？好的 很多人点头 很好
OK, that's equal to 2r plus two of size of A minus,
好的 这个等于2r加上两倍A减去
OK, I want to plug in for B,
好的 我想把B代入
and it turns out very nicely.
结果会好看一点
I have an equation involving A, B, and r.
我有一个关于A B和r的式子
So, I get rid of the variable size of B
我想消掉B的大小这个变量
by just plugging that in.
所以要把B代入
OK, and so what do I plug in here?
好的 那这里我怎么代入？
What's B equal to?
B等于什么？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Yeah, r minus size of A minus one.
[教授]:对了 r-|A|-1
I wrote it the other way.
我用另外一种形式写出来
OK, and then plus t_i.
然后加上t_i
OK, and this is since r is A plus B plus one.
由于r等于A加B加1
OK, everybody with me still?
好的 大家思路都跟上了吗？
I'm just doing algebra.
刚才只是代数运算
We've got to make sure we do the algebra right.
我们要确保式子是对的
OK, so that's equal to,
好的 那这个等于
let's just multiply all this out now and get 2r plus,
我们把里面的全部乘出来得到 2r加上
I have 2A here minus A.
加上2A 这里减A
So, that's 4A.
所以是4A
And then, two times minus r is minus 2r.
然后 2乘以负r等于负2r
Two times minus one is minus two.
2乘以-1等于-2
Oh, but it's minus-minus two,
但它减去负二
so it's plus two.
所以是正二
OK, and then I have 2t_i.
好的 我有2t_i
So, that's just algebra.
这些都是代数运算
OK, so that's not bad.
所以 这个还不错
We've just got rid of another variable.
我们刚刚还消除了另一个变量
What variable did we get rid of? r.
是哪个变量？r
It didn't matter what the rank was
排位是多少并不影响
as long as I knew what the number of inversions was here.
只要我知道这里的逆序对的数量就够了
OK, so that's now equal to 4A plus two plus 2t_i.
好的 现在它等于4A加上2加上2t_i
And, that's less than or equal to, I claim,
而且 还小于等于 根据前面的
four times r star plus t_i using our other fact.
4倍的r*与t_i的和
Since r star is equal to
因为r*等于
the size of A plus the size of C, plus one,
A的大小加上C的大小 再加一
then that's greater than or equal to the size of A plus one.
它大于或等于的大小A加1
OK, if I look at this,
好的 我在算这条式时
I'm basically looking at A.
我基本上都在算A
The fact that A, what did I do here?
这个A... 我做了些什么？
So we have r star is greater than or equal to A plus one, right,
我们有r*大于或等于A加1 对吧
so therefore, A plus one, good.
所以有A加1 好
so this is basically less than or equal to 4A plus four,
那么这里就是小于等于4A+4
which is four times A plus one.
也就是4倍的A加1
I probably should have put in another algebra step here,
我这里应该再写多一步
OK, because if I can't verify it like this,
因为如果我没有验算一下的话
then I get nervous.
我会感觉不踏实
This is basically, at most, 4A plus four.
这里最大等于4A+4
That's four times A plus one,
其实是4倍的A+1
and A plus one is less than or equal to r star.
A+1是小于等于r*的
And then, 2t_i is, at most, 4TI.
2ti 最大不超过4t_i
So, I've got this.
所以我得到这个
Does everybody see where that came from?
大家都看懂了这是怎么来的吗？
But what is r star plus t_i?
但是r*加t_i等于多少？
What is r star plus t_i?
r*加t_i等于多少？
What is it?
是多少？
It's c_i star.
它等于c_i
That's just c_i star.
它就是c_i
So, the amortized cost of i'th operation is,
所以操作i的平摊代价
at most, four times opt's cost.
最大不超过最优算法代价的4倍
OK, that's pretty remarkable.
真的很强大
OK, so amortized cost of the i'th operation
好的 操作i的平摊代价
is just four times opt's cost.
刚好是最优算法代价的4倍
Now, of course, we have to now go through
当然 现在我们要检查一遍
and analyze the total cost.
并分析总的代价
But this is now the routine way that
但这已经是例行公事了
we analyze things with a potential function.
我们用势函数来分析
So, the costs of MTF of S is just the summation
根据定义 MTF的代价就等于
of the individual costs, OK, by definition.
所有单步代价的总和
And that is just the sum, i equals one to S
这就是那个和 i从1到S
of the amortized cost plus the
它的平摊代价加上
minus the change in potential.
负的势能变化
OK, did I do this right?
呃 我做对了吗？
No, I put the parentheses in the wrong place.
不对 我的括号放错位置了
Now I've got it right. Good.
现在是对的了 好
I just missed a parenthesis.
我刚漏了一个括号
OK, so this is,
所以说
so in the past what I did was I expressed the amortized cost
之前那条式里 我是把平摊代价表示为
as being equal to c_i plus the change in potential.
c_i加上势能的变化
I'm just throwing these two terms over to the other side
现在我只是把这两项移到等号另一边去
and saying what's the true cost in terms of the amortized cost?
这次我们是看 实际代价怎么用平摊代价来表示？
OK, so I get c hat of i plus phi sub L_i minus one
好的 所以我得出的是c^i加上ΦL_(i-1)
minus phi of L_i, OK, by making that substitution.
再减去ΦL_i  移项后是变成这样
OK, that's less than or equal to since this is linear.
所以它小于或等于... 因为它是线性的
Well, I know what the sum of the amortized cost is.
我又知道平摊代价的总和是多少
It's, at most, 4c_i star.
最大等于4c_i
So, the sum of them is, at most,
所以它们的和最大等于
to that sum, i equals one to S of 4c_i star.
i从1到S 4c_i*的总和
And then, as happens in all these things,
然后 所有的这些项
you get a telescope with these terms.
你都可以用缩进
Every term is added in once and subtracted out once,
每一项被加进去一次 又被减去一次
except for the ones at the limit.
除了两个边界项之外
So, I get plus phi of L_0
所以 我要加上ΦL_0
minus phi of L sub cardinality of S.
减去ΦL_S
And now, this term is zero.
现在 已知这一项是0
And this term is greater than or equal to zero.
而这一项是大于等于0的
OK, so therefore this whole thing is less than or equal to,
因此整个式子小于等于
well, what's that?
咦 是多少？
That's just four times opt's cost.
刚好就是最优算法代价的4倍
And so, we're four competitive.
所以 得出它是4竞争的
OK, this is amazing, I think.
好吧 我都觉得很神奇
It's not that hard, OK,
其实不难 好的
but it's quite amazing that just by doing a simple heuristic,
但是仅仅用了一个简单的启发式
you're nearly as good as any
性能就变得
omniscient algorithm could possibly be.
像上帝算法那么好
OK, you're nearly as good.
已经差不多那么好了
And, in fact, in practice, this is a great heuristic.
实际上 这是一个很强大的启发式
So, if ever you have things like a hash table that
假如说你有个哈希表
you're actually seeing by chaining, OK,
如果你用的是链接法
often it's the case that if when you access the elements,
通常当你访问一个元素时
you're just bringing them up to the front of the list
你就把它移到链表的表头
if it's an unsorted list that you've put them into,
如果一开始它是无序的链表
just bring them up to the front.
那就把它们移到前面
You can easily save 30 to 40% in run time
这就可以节省30%到40%的时间
for the accessing to the hash table
来访问哈希表
because you will be much more likely to find the elements inside.
因为你会更容易找到里面的元素
Of course, it depends on the distribution and so forth,
当然 这也取决于元素的分布
for empirical matters, but the point is that
实际用用才知道 但有一点就是
you are not going to be too far off from
你这样做得到的排列顺序
the ordering that an optimal algorithm would do,
不会和最优算法的顺序差太多
optimal off-line algorithm: I mean, amazing.
最优离线算法 所以说 很犀利
OK: optimal off-line.
离线是最优的
Now, it turns out that in the reading that we assigned,
接下来 看到我们发的阅读材料
so, we assigned you Sleator and Tarjan's original paper.
我发给你们的是B.T.大.神.的原论文
In that reading,
在论文里
they actually have a slightly different model
他们用了一个稍稍不同的模型
where they count transposes that move in access element x
他们把访问x时的置换操作...
towards the front of the list as free.
把置换到表头的代价 记为0
OK, so, and this basically models,
好的 这种建模基本上...
so here's the idea is if I actually have a linked list,
它的思路是 如果我实际有一个链表
and when I chase down, once I find x,
当我依次数下来 找到x的时候
I can actually move x up to the front
我把它移到表头的代价
with just a constant number of pointer operations
只是一两步常数级的指针运算
to splice it out and put it up to the front.
把它的指针指向表头就好了
I don't actually have to transpose all way back down.
我实际上用不着一路挨个地交换
OK, so that's kind of the model that they use,
所以 他们用的是这样的模型
which is a more realistic model.
更有实践意义
OK, I presented this argument because it's a little bit simpler.
我之所以讲这个命题 是因为它更为简单
OK, and the model is a little bit simpler.
这个模型挺简单的
But in their model, they have,
但在他们的模型里
when you access something,
当你访问某些元素时
you want to bring it up to the front,
你想把它移到前面去
or anything that you happen to go across during that time,
或者当你正好在访问的时候
you could bring up to the front essentially for free.
你可以不耗费时间地把它移到前面
This model is the splicing in,
这模型把链表拆分
splicing x in and out of L in constant time.
用常数时间来完成x的拆放
Then, MTF is, it turns out, two competitive.
然后 这样的MTF就是 双竞争的
It's within a factor of two of optimal,
它是两倍的最优算法代价
OK, if you use that.
好的 如果你用这个
And that's actually a good exercise to work through.
这个用来当作业布置很不错
You could also go read about it in the reading
你也可以读读论文
to understand this better,
更好地理解它
to look to see where you would use those things.
想一想你要怎么使用这些东西
You have to have another term representing the number of,
你要用另外一项来表示这个
quote, "free" transposes.
免费的置换操作
But it turns out that
但是很明显
all the math works out pretty much the same.
这些数学工作都差不多
OK, let's see, another thing I promised you is,
另外 我答应过你们的
what if, to look at the case,
如果 这例子里
what if they don't start with the same lists?
如果一开始是两个不同的表 那怎么办？
OK, what if the two lists are different when they start?
它们从一开始就不一样 那怎么办？
Then, the potential function at the beginning might be
那么 一开始的势函数就可能
as big as what?
等于多少？
How big are the potential function start out as
初始的势函数会有多大
if the lists are different?
如果两个表不同的话？
So, suppose we're starting out,
那么 假设我们一开始
you have a list, and opt says,
你有个列表 然后最优算法说
OK, I'm going to start out by ordering my list
好的 我要根据接下来的访问序列
according to the sequence that I want to use,
将列表调整为我想要的顺序
OK, and MTF orders it according to the sequence it must use.
好的 MTF根据序列也重新排列
What list is opt going to start out with as an adversary?
对于我们的宿敌来说 什么才是他初始的最优表？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Yeah, it's going to pick the reverse
[教授]:对 它都打算采用和mtf相反的序列
of whatever MTF starts out with, right,
无论MTF的初始序列是怎么样
because then, if he picks the reverse,
因为 如果他的是反向的
what's the number of inversions?
逆序对的数量是多少？
It's how many inversions in a reverse ordered list?
反向的列表有多少逆序对？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Yeah, n choose two, OK.
[教授]:C(n,2) 好的
Is it n choose two, or n minus one choose two?
是C(n,2)的组合 还是C(n-1,2)的组合
n minus one choose two, OK,
C(n-1,2)的组合 好的
inversions that you get
你得到的逆序对
because it's basically a triangular number
它其实是杨辉三角数
when you add them up.
当你把它们加起来
But in any case, it's order n^2, worst case.
最坏情况是n^2
So, what does that do to our analysis here?
那它对我们的分析有什么影响？
It says that the cost of MTF of S is going to be,
MTF对于序列S上的代价
well, this is no longer zero.
呃 不再是0了
This is now n^2. OK,
现在是n^2
so we get that costs of MTF of S is, at most,
我们得到 S上的MTF算法的代价 最大不超过
four times opt's thing plus order n^2, OK?
4倍的最优算法代价 加上n^2阶 对吧？
And, if we look at the definition,
然后 如果我们看这个定义
did we erase it already?
我擦掉了吗？
I erase the definition of competitive.
我又擦掉了一个竞争性的定义
OK, this is still four competitive, OK,
好吧 它仍然是4竞争的
since n^2 is constant as the size of S goes to infinity.
因为当S趋向无穷时 n^2是常数级的
This is, once again, sort of your notion of,
这个是.. 又要考考你们了
what does it mean to be a constant?
n^2是常数级的是什么意思？
OK, so as the size of the list gets bigger,
即使列表越变越大
all we're doing is accessing
但我们做的仅仅是访问
whatever that number, n, is of elements.
无论这个数字n多大
That number doesn't grow with the problem size,
它的大小并不随着问题的规模变化
OK, even if it starts out as some variable number, n.
好的 即便它一开始是个变量n
OK, it doesn't grow with the problem size.
它并不随问题的规模而变化
We still end up being competitive.
我们仍然用竞争性来得出结果
This is just the k that was in that definition of competitiveness.
这就是竞争性定义里面的k
OK, any questions? Yeah?
好的 有问题吗？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:Well, so you could change the cost model a little bit.
[教授]:嗯 那么你们把模型的代价改变一下
[Prof]:Yeah. And that's a good one to work out.
[教授]:是的 这是个好方法
But if you say the cost of transposing,
但如果说到置换的代价
so, the cost of transposing is probably moving two pointers,
它可能只是移动了两个指针
Approximately. No.
大约是 不对
one, three pointers.
一个...三个指针
So, suppose that the cost of,
所以 假设这个代价等于
wow, that's a good exercise, OK?
哇噢 是个好作业题 对吧？
Suppose the cost was three times to do a transpose,
假设置换的代价是3次
was three times the cost of doing an access,
一次访问的代价变成3次
of following a pointer.
用指针访问
OK, how would that change the number here?
好 这样改变了什么数？
OK, good exercise, great exercise.
好的 好练习 好练习
OK, hmm, good final question.
一想到这儿我都流口水了
OK, yes, it will affect the constant here
没错 它会影响到这个常数项
just as when we do the free transpose,
就像B.T.大.神.用的免费置换一样
when we move things towards the front,
我们把元素置换到前面
that we consider those as free, OK.
不过把它看成是免费的
Those operations end up reducing the constant as well.
你说的操作也会减少这个常数
OK, but the point is that
但是有一点
this constant is independent of the constant
这个常数和表中元素的数量
having to do with the number of elements in the list.
这两个常数之间是相互独立的
So that's a different constant.
所以 这是另外一个常数
So, this is a constant.
这是个常数
OK, and so as with a lot of these things,
世事可以分两种
there's two things. One is, there's the theory.
两样东西 一个是理论
So, theory here backs up practice.
理论支撑实践
OK, those practitioners knew what they were doing,
实践者知道他们在做些什么
OK, without knowing what they were doing.
或是连自己在做什么都不知道
OK, so that's really good. OK,
所以 这样很好很和谐
and we have a deeper understanding that's led to,
现在 我们有了更深入的认识了
as I say, many algorithms for things like,
正如我说的 许多算法 比如
the important ones are like paging.
比如像分页这种重要的算法
So, what's the common page replacement policy that people study,
人们一般学习的分页置换策略是什么？
people have at most operating systems?
有学操作系统的人吗？
Who's done 6.033 or something?
谁上过6.033的课程？
Yeah, it's Least Recently Used, LRU.
对了 "最近最少使用策略" LRU
People have heard of that, OK.
大家都听过的了
So, you can analyze LRU competitive,
你可以分析LRU的竞争性
and show that LRU is actually competitive
证明LRU也是很不错的
with optimal page replacement under certain assumptions.
即使是跟某种假设下的理想的换页策略来对比
OK, and there are also other things.
好的 还有别的东西
Like, people do random replacement algorithms,
比如 人们采用随机换页算法
and there are a whole bunch of other kinds of things
还有其他许多诸如此类的
that can be analyzed with the competitive analysis framework.
都可以在竞争分析这个框架下完成分析
OK, so it's very cool stuff.
所以这一套真的很无解
And, we are going to see more in recitation on Friday,
星期五的复习课会接触到
see a couple of other really good problems
一些别的更好玩得问题
that are maybe a little bit easier than this one,
可能会比这个要简单一些
OK, definitely easier than this one.
好吧 肯定比这个简单
they give you hopefully some more intuition about competitive analysis.
肯定能让你们对竞争分析有很大的启发
I also want to warn you about next week's problem set.
我还要提醒你们 关于下周的习题集
So, next week's problem set
那么 下周的习题集
has a programming assignment on it.
有一道是编程题
OK, and the programming assignment is mandatory,
这份编程作业是必做的
meaning, well, all the problem sets are mandatory as you know,
也就是说 你们懂的
but if you decide not to do a problem
如果不做这道编程题
there's a little bit of a penalty
平时分要扣分
and then the penalties scale dramatically
而且如果你不做作业
as you stop doing problem sets.
会扣很多平时分
But this one is mandatory-mandatory.
但是这题是必做中的战斗题
OK, you don't pass the class.
不做就挂科
You'll get an incomplete if you do not do this programming assignment.
如果你不做你的人参就是不完整的
Now, I know that some people are less practiced with programming.
现在 我知道有些同学很少敲代码
And so, what I encourage you to do over the weekend
所以 我建议你周末时候
is spent a few minutes
花点时间
and work on your programming skills
敲敲代码
if you're not up to snuff in programming.
如果你已经敲到条件反射的境界
It's not going to be a long assignment,
这个作业只是一眨眼的事
but if you don't know how to read a file and write out a file,
但如果你是传说中的亚历山大 读写文件都不会
and be able to write a dozen lines of code, OK,
半天才挤出一两行代码
if you are weak on that,
如果你很水
this weekend would be a good idea to practice
这周末就是个升级刷经验的好机会
reading in a text file.
读文件
It's going to be a text file.
到时候是要读文件的
Read it in a text file,
从文件里面读数据
do some manipulations,
然后做些操作
write out a text file, OK?
再写回到文件里 好吧？
So, I don't want people to get caught with this being mandatory
我不希望有人连必做题都做不完
and that not have time to finish it
然后还被我抓到
because they are busy trying to...eh...
因为他们总是想着
trying to learn how to program in short order.
能够走捷径
I know some people take this course
我知道有人上这门课之前
without quite getting all the programming prerequisites.
还没怎么编过程
Here's where you need it. Question?
但现在你要用到了 有问题吗？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
[Prof]:No language limitations. Pick your language.
[教授]:没有语言限制 随你
The answer will be written in, I think, Java,
官方答案可能会用 我想 用Java写
and Eric has graciously volunteered to use Python
然后Eric最喜欢用Python
for his solution to this problem.
来写他的答案了
We'll see whether he lives up to that promise.
我们看他到时是不是这么专一
You did already?
你已经写好了？
OK, and George wrote the Java solution.
George君说要用Java的
And so, C is fine.
还有 C语言也可以
Matlab is fine.
Matlab也可以
OK, what else is fine?
还有什么呢？
Anything is fine.
都是可以的
Scheme is fine. Scheme is great.
Scheme可以 Scheme好东西
OK, so any such things will be just fine.
这些东西都可以用
So, we don't care what language you program in,
我不介意你们用什么语言
but you will have to do programming to solve this problem.
当你们就是要用编程来解决这些问题
OK, so thanks very much.
好的 非常感谢
See you next week.
下周见